<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Whereas His Majesty by letters patents under his great seal of Ireland, bearing date the eighteenth day of May in the two and thirtieth year of his reign, hath been graciously pleased to grant unto Sir Thomas Armestrong,  Knight, and Colonel George Legg, their executors, administrators and assigns, full, free and absolute licence, power and authority, that they by themselves ... should ... make in some convenient place or places ... such quantity of halfpence of copper as might by them be issued amongst His Majesties subjects ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Ormonde.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1677-1685 : Ormonde)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16149419</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16149419</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104875</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104875)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1595:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Whereas His Majesty by letters patents under his great seal of Ireland, bearing date the eighteenth day of May in the two and thirtieth year of his reign, hath been graciously pleased to grant unto Sir Thomas Armestrong,  Knight, and Colonel George Legg, their executors, administrators and assigns, full, free and absolute licence, power and authority, that they by themselves ... should ... make in some convenient place or places ... such quantity of halfpence of copper as might by them be issued amongst His Majesties subjects ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Ormonde.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1677-1685 : Ormonde)</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke and John Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from first 14 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Statement of responsibility transposed from head of title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Given at the Council-chamber in Dublin the 19th day of July, 1680"--leaf [2]</note>
                  <note>Broadside in [3] leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mints --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Coinage --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1775.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104875:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure/> BY THE Lord Lieutenant AND COUNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ORMONDE.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS His Majeſty by Letters Patents under His Great Seal of <hi>Ireland,</hi> bearing Date the Eighteenth day of <hi>May</hi> in the Two and thirtieth year of His Reign, hath been graciouſly pleaſed to grant unto Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> Knight, and Colonel <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, full, free and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Licence, power and authority, That they by themſelves, or by their ſufficient Deputy or Deputies, Workmen and Servants, ſhould [during the term of One and twenty years, to commence from the Date of the ſaid Letters Patents] make in ſome convenient place or places, at his and their and every of their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and appointment ſuch quantity of Halfpence of Copper as might by them be iſſued amongſt His Majeſties Subjects in this His Majeſties Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> during the time aforeſaid, and them to utter, iſſue, diſperſe and diſpoſe of within and throughout this Kingdom. And to the intent the ſaid Copper Halfpence might be diſtinguiſhed from any other, which have been made, or might happen to be made in any other place or places whatſoever, hath declared his Royal will and pleaſure, and commanded that the ſaid Halfpence ſhould be made of Copper, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:104875:2"/>
on the one ſide the Figure or Effigies of His Majeſties Head ſtampt in Copper, and on the other ſide the ſtamp or impreſs of an Harp Crowned, with this Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on round before and on the Reverſe ſide, <hi>Carolus Secundus Dei gratia, Magnae Britanniae, Franciae &amp; Hiberniae Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas His Majeſty in and by His ſaid Letters Patents, hath willed and ordained that the ſaid Copper Halfpence ſo made ſhould weigh each Halfpeny One hundred and ten grains Troy weight, and that the ſame ſhould be generally uſed by all His Subjects, and others in this His Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> as Tokens of the value of Halfpence within this Kingdom; and to the intent that the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns reſpectively might have and enjoy the full advantage, benefit and profit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them by His Majeſties ſaid Grant, His Majeſty hath been graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in and by His ſaid Letters Patents, ſtraightly to forbid and prohibit all and every perſon and perſons whatſoever, other than the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and the ſaid <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, Agents and Servants, to make or counterfeit any ſuch Copper Halfpence, or to make or uſe any Engines, Stamps or Inſtruments, whereby they may be made, or to make or uſe any other Tokens, Engines, Stamps or Inſtruments in reſemblance of them, or any other Tokens whatſoever, or to uſe or utter any other Halfpenny-tokens, Pence, or Farthing-tokens, or Copper-pieces, or Braſs-pieces, or pieces of any other Metal which have been or ſhall be made for Tokens for the uſe of any part of His Majeſties Dominions, or any the parts beyond the Seas, or which have been made either before, or ſhall be made after the Date of His Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents, within this His Majeſties ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or in any other parts, or to import or bring into this His Majeſties Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> any Halfpence, Pence, or Farthing-tokens, or Copper or Braſs-pieces, or pieces of any other Metal which have been or ſhall be made in any parts beyond the Seas to be uſed as Tokens, upon pain of Forfeiture of all ſuch Halfpenny-to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, Farthing-tokens, or other Tokens, or pieces of Copper or Braſs or other Metal which hath been or ſhall be made and uſed as Tokens, and of all ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, Stamps and Inſtruments as ſhould be ſo made, uſed or found contrary to His Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents, and upon ſuch further pains, penalties and impriſonments as by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, and His Majeſties Prerogative Royal may be inflicted upon ſuch perſons for their contempt and breach of His Majeſties Royal Commands in this behalf, the one moyety of all ſuch Forfeitures to be to His Majeſtie, his Heirs and Succeſſors; and the other moyety to the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns reſpectively.</p>
            <p>And whereas His Majeſty in and by His ſaid Letters Patents hath further granted unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Executors, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators and Aſſigns reſpectively, that they by themſelves, their Deputies, Servants and Agents, or any of them, may from time to time, and at all times during the ſaid term of Twenty one years [calling a Conſtable or other Officer with him or them] enter into any Ship, Bottom, Veſſel or Boat, or into any Houſe, Shop, Cellar, Warehouſe, or any other place whatſoever within this Kingdom, where they or any of them ſhall have cauſe to make ſearch by water or land (as well within Liberties as without) and there to try and ſearch by all ways and means for all Counterfeit Halfpence, Farthing-tokens, and Pence, and other Tokens of Braſs or Copper, or other Metal whatſoever, which have been made, or ſhall be uſed as Tokens, or any Engines, Stamps or Inſtruments, that are already made, or ſhall at any time after the date of His Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents be made, for the making, coyning, ſtamping or caſting of any Farthing-tokens, Halfpence or Pence whatſoever, or as ſhall be brought from other parts of His Majeſties Dominions, or the parts beyond the Seas, or found to be made within His Majeſties ſaid Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> contrary to the meaning of His Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents, and that finding any ſuch Tokens, Copper and Braſs pieces, Inſtruments, Stamps or Engines, to arreſt, ſeiſe, carry away and detain the ſame to the uſes in His Majeſties Letters Patents before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:104875:3"/>Theſe are therefore in His Majeſties Name, ſtraightly to command and forbid all manner of perſons whatſoever, that they and every of them do forbear to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, make, ſtamp, caſt, coyn, utter or receive any Copper-halfpence, or Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-pence, or Farthing-tokens, or any other Tokens whatſoever of any ſort of metal, or pieces of Copper or Braſs by way of Change or otherwiſe, or to have or uſe any Engines, Stamps or Inſtruments, whereby ſuch Copper-halfpence, or Pence, or Farthing-tokens, or other pieces of Copper or Braſs may be ſtamped, coined, made or uttered, or uſed amongſt His Majeſties Subjects in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, contrary to his Majeſties will and pleaſure declared in and by his Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents, as they will anſwer the contrary at their utmoſt perils, ſave only the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and the ſaid Colonel <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Deputies, Agents and Servants, who are hereby required to make ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient quantity of the ſaid Copper-halfpence for the uſe of his Majeſties Subjects, and to take care that each of them do weigh One hundred and ten grains Troy weight, as in his Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents are directed, and to ſend ſuch proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them into as many Cities, Burroughs, Corporate and Market towns of this Kingdom, as they ſhall think convenient for the uſe of his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in this Kingdom, the ſame to be left in the hands of ſome diſcreet perſon or perſons whom they ſhall appoint, to be vended and uttered amongſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the reſpective Cities, Burroughs, Counties and places of this Realm; and in caſe any of his Majeſties Subjects ſhall happen to be ſurcharged in the courſe of their Trades with more of the ſaid Copper-halfpence, then they can utter, then the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and the ſaid Colonel <hi>George Legg</hi> their Deputies, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents &amp; Servants are in purſuance of his Majeſties ſaid Letters Patents hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to deliver at any time during the term aforeſaid, the ſumme of Twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings currant monies, for every ſumme of Twenty one ſhillings returned in the ſame Copper halfpence unto ſuch perſon and perſons who ſhall ſo happen to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and ſo after that rate for all greater ſummes.</p>
            <p>And we do further in his Majeſties Name ſtraightly command and require, That the aforeſaid Copper-halfpence which have been and ſhall be made by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royal Authority according to his Majeſties ſaid Grant (and no other To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken whatſoever) be uttered, uſed, received, accepted and taken in all Dealings whereby Exchange of ſmall Money is neceſſary between man and man, as currant Monies, according to the value of Halfpence within this Kingdom, yet ſo as none of his Majeſties Subjects are hereby compelled to receive of the ſaid Copper-half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in any payment of Money above Five ſhillings in One hundred pounds, and ſo proportionably in all greater or leſſer ſummes: and the chief Officers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, with the Miniſters and Conſtables of all places within this Realm reſpectively, and alſo the Farmers, Collectors and Receivers of his Majeſties Revenue of this Kingdom for the time being, are hereby required to endeavour that the ſaid Copper-halfpence may be uttered and diſperſed throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that they be freely received and paſs in uſe betwixt man and man for the value of Halfpence in the way of Exchange as is before expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And we do further in his Majeſties Name ſtraightly charge and command all and ſingular Mayors, Sheriffs, Iuſtices of the Peace, Conſtables, Headbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Controllers, Cuſtomers and Searchers, and all other his Majeſties Officers and Miniſters to whom it ſhall or may appertain to be aiding and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all lawful and convenient manner unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Armeſtrong</hi> and Colonel <hi>George Legg,</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, and their and every of their Deputies, Factors, Agents and Servants in the due Execution of the Premiſſes upon pain of his Majeſties high Diſpleaſure, and ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Impriſonments as by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, and his Majeſties Prerogative Royal, can or may be inflicted upon them for their contempt in that behalf.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the <hi>Council-chamber</hi> in <hi>Dublin</hi>
                  <date>the 19th day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mich: Armach: C.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hen: Midenſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo: Davys.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arran.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ca: Dillon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wm: Flower.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bleſinton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Keatinge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lanesborough.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>He: Hene.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke</hi> and <hi>John Crooke,</hi> Printers to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, at His Majeſties Printing-Houſe in <hi>Skinner-row.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
